Finding aid to the George Brendan Dowell Papers CA.MS.00070
Smith College Archives
George Brendan Dowell Papers
1920-1961
Smith College Archives
Dowell, George Brendan.
CA.MS.00070
0.208 linear feet (1 container)
Assistant Professor of Theater. Collection contains biographical material, photographs, and publications.
Biographical Note
George Brendan Dowell was born on December 15, 1909 in New York City to David J. Dowell and Mary Kelly Dowell. He attended the Institute of Fine Arts, studying the history of fine arts, before attending the Yale University School of Fine Arts Department of Drama, where he received a diploma in 1933. He received a BS from New York University in 1944, an MA in 1946 and an E.DD from Columbia University.
Before coming to Smith as a Visiting Lecturer of Theatre in 1949, Dowell worked in Hollywood as a script advisor and playwright, as well as working for Paramount Pictures from 1935-36, where he co-authored two original motion pictures. From 1937-38 he worked as the general stage director at the American Showshop at the President Theatre in New York City. During the war, from 1943-44, he worked in the administration of the Army Air Forces, and received a letter of commendation. From 1944-45 he worked as the night cashier at the Bursar's Office of NYU. In 1950, he became an Assistant Professor of Theatre at Smith College. During the summer of 1951, Dowell was a staff member at the Plymouth Rock Center of Music and Drama, and also worked at the Duxbury Playhouse in Massachusetts as a guest stage director. During the summer of 1953, Dowell returned to Hollywood to work at the Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Studios as a scenario writer. Dowell had also served as the co-director of the Bryn Mawr College Summer Theatre, and directed plays at the Bryn Mawr Summer Playhouse.
Dowell wrote several plays, including "The Great God Innis", an Irish folk comedy which he wrote in collaboration with Helen R. Loenthal, which premiered in 1949- 50, "Lefty Strikes Her Out", and "Old Greenhorn", which received the John Golden Playwrighting Award. Along with Hallie Flannagan Davis, he edited "Heritage", an original historical play written and produced for the 75th Anniversary of Smith college in 1950. Dowell also published several articles in Players Magazine and other theatrical publications.
Dowell was a member of the Dramatists' Guild of the Author's League of American from 1933-49, as well as was a member of the Yale Alumni in Drama club from 1940-49, and the Columbia Alumni Federation from 1948-49. He also served as a member of the script committee for the Tercentenary Celebration of Northampton, and served as chair of the pageant committee. In 1954, he became director of the American College Players.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George Brendan Dowell papers contain biographical materials, photographs and publications spanning Dowell's career as a faculty member of the Theater Department at Smith College.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into three series:
Series I. Biographical Materials
Series II. Photographs
Series III. Publications
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Dowell, George Brendan.
- Series I. Biographical Materials
  Scope and Contents
  This part of the collection contains general background biographical information and newspaper articles about Dowell.
  - Biographical Material, 1948 - 1958 (Box 768, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Material: Newspaper articles, 1949 - 1961 (Box 768, Folder 2)
- Series II. Photographs
  This section of the collection contains one folder of undated photographs.
  - Photographs, n. d. (Box 768, Folder 3)
- Series III. Publications
  This section of the collection consists of background material, publicity, scripts, correspondence relating to the publications and the publications themselves.
  - "The Second College Theater Tour of England", 1955 (Box 768, Folder 4)
  - "Covenant"
    - Scripts, n. d. (Box 768, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 768, Folder 6)
    - Theater 35a, notes and background material, 1952 (Box 768, Folder 7)
  - "Heritage"
    - Background, productions and Correspondence, 1920; 1950 (Box 768, Folder 8)
    - Publicity, 1950 (Box 768, Folder 9)
    - Scripts, 1949 - 1950 (Box 768, Folder 10)